Lewis J. Myers Papers VHP2005/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
Lewis J. Myers Papers
Bulk, 1944-1946
1944-1946, 2004-2005
VHP2005/4
CCSU Veterans History Project
16.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This Collection details Lewis Myer’s experiences and recollections during World War II which he was drafted into the United States Army in 1944. As a member of the 2nd Division, 38th Infantry, he served in France, Germany and Czechoslovakia. The Collection contains personal service records, a hand drawn map and photographs. Dating from 1944 thru 1946,and oral history interview conducted on 2005.
Myers, Lewis J., 1926 -
Biographical/Historical note
Luis J. Myers was drafted into the U.S. Army in 1944. At the time he was living in New Brunswick, Canada, however, he was a legal resident of the United States. He went to Camp Croft (SC) for basic training. He was trained as infantry and his division was sent to Europe as replacements just after the invasion in Normandy. His division fought on the front lines in France and Germany. The soldiers marched from France to Frankfurt and then Berlin. Myers slept mainly in foxholes, and ate K-rations for almost every meal. He describes in detail the conditions and tense situations that the soldiers were faced with on a daily basis. When the fighting ceased in Germany his division was sent to Czechoslovakia, where they picked up surrendering German soldiers. Myers' division was also responsible for the liberation of a women's concentration camp in Czechoslovakia. The soldiers interviewed the prisoners to find out what they had gone through, and were then given passage home. Upon his return to the United States, he had to undergo surgery on his leg to remove shrapnel that was embedded from combat. After the operation, his division was to be moved to the Pacific Theater; however, the war with Japan ended at this time, and he remained in the United States instead. After Myers' discharge in 1946, he married and went to work at Pratt and Whitney as an electrician, where he remained for 27 years before his retirement. He is also a member of the American Legion and the DAV. He remains active with the DAV where he is a service officer, enabling him to help other disabled veterans.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 38th.; United States. Army.; Camp Croft (Spartanburg, S.C.); Czechoslovakia; Fort Devens (Mass.); France; Germany; Interviews; Manuscript; Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Europe; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Czechoslovakia; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/4.I
  - Certificate of Honorable Discharge, 8 July 1946; VHP2005/4.I.1
  - Separation and Qualification record, 1946; VHP2005/4.I.2
  - Enlisted Record and Report of Separation/Honorable Discharge, 1946; VHP2005/4.I.3
  - Hand drawn map of Lewis Myer’s travels while in Europe. Includes annotations and location key, VHP2005/4.I.4
  - Interview Synopsis, March 26, 2005; VHP2005/4.I.5
- Series II: Multi-Media, VHP2005/4.II
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/4.II
    - Lewis Myers in uniform, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.1
    - Lewis Myers with his sister Alma and niece before shipping overseas, Quebec, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.2
    - Lewis Myers with his sister Laura in a horse drawn carriage, Quebec, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.3
    - Lewis Myers, Quebec, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.4
    - Lewis Myers with his sister Doris, New York City, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.5
    - Lewis Myers on furlough before shipping overseas, New York City, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.6
    - Lewis Myers with a Czechoslovakian school teacher, 1944; VHP2005/4.II.7
    - James Waterhouse (left) and Lewis Myers (right), Camp Swift, Texas, circa 1946; VHP2005/4.II.8
    - Father Joseph Barry, Camp Swift, Texas, March 26, 1946; VHP2005/4.II.9
    - Father Joseph Barry at the Chapel of “The Rock,” Camp Swift, Texas, circa 1946; VHP2005/4.II.10
    - Lewis Myers with young neighbor boy Dalton, 2004; VHP2005/4.II.11
  - Subseries B: Moving images, VHP2005/4.IIb
    - Interview Synopsis, March 26, 2005; VHP2005/4.IIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/4, Box VHP Interview #1)